[SPEAKER_00] As-salamu alaykum wa rahmatullahi wa barakatuh. We're waiting for you to walk in. Bismillah ar-Rahman ar-Rahim. Nuh-mahduhu nus-sani ala rasoolin kareem ma ba'al. Okay, so I gave you some homework last time, right? So hopefully we did it this time, inshallah. Yes, some of us? Who did the homework? Only three, four, five people? Six, seven? Okay, not too bad, but not what I expected. Inshallah. So, let's start from Thameen number one. Let's go over it. Did we do this? No, we didn't do this, right? We didn't go through it. Page 56. We didn't go through it yet, right? Okay. Okay. Bismillah ar-Rahman ar-Rahim. Bismillah ar-Rahman ar-Rahim. So, yeah,
[SPEAKER_00] this is just you have to answer the question, right? So, okay, masmuka? Loud, louder. Yeah, you don't have to say ana, because it's just, when you say ismi, it's already understood that it's your name. So you just say ismi mudathir. Okay, good. Abdullah? Min aina anta? Okay, good. Hafiz, well? Maa loogatuka? Loogati al-injleezia. Good. Loogati al-injleezia or al-injleezia. Hafiz Haroon. Aina abook? Is that how that means? Where? Okay. Oh, where is your dad? Abooka. Where's your dad? No, there's no where you're from. Oh, where's your dad? Yeah. Yeah. So, abu just means father. Abooka means? My. Yeah, your, not my, your. Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] So, where's your father? Aina abooka. Yeah. Oh, you're asking me? Yeah, I'm asking you. Abooka. How do you say the car name? You know it. Oh, abooka say, yeah. No, my father's not a car, no. No, so you say, my father is in, how do you say in something? In. Please, nobody tell him. Because that's how he'll get it, but if you let him think himself, he'll get it. He's a hafiz, Mashallah, he's a smart guy. Ala? No, ala means on. What's in? You know, you know it. Come on, think, think. B? Yes, good. Oh, okay. Abooka. No, not my, we're talking about your father, not my father. Oh, abi? Yeah, good. Abi means? You just called my father a car, you should know what I mean. Oh, yeah. Abi fi sayyarati. Very good, Mashallah. Abi fi sayyarati. Okay,
[SPEAKER_00] good. All right. Wali? Aina umuka? Aina fi. No, so Aina is the question, right? So you don't have to repeat Aina in the answer because it means where. So you're just responding where she is, so you don't have to say Aina in the answer. Ummi fi. Wa alaikum assalam. Fi sayyarati. Okay, ummi fi sayyarati. Okay, good, yeah. Yeah, ummi fi sayyarati. Good. Wa alaikum assalam. Alaka akhun? Alaka akhun? Where is your brother? No, there's no where. Alaka. Oh, no, is this? Is this your brother? No, the lamb is for what? What does lamb indicate? Belonging or possession, right? So laka means you. So, what would it mean? Are you my brother? No, alaka. Laka, like, so you add lamb to whatever is being possessed or belonging to,
[SPEAKER_00] right? So, for example, Saim has one house, right? So you say li to indicate possession. So, over here the lamb is connected to ka, you. So, it's asking about what you possess or what you have. You get it? Right, right. So, alaka akhun is his brother, right? Yeah. So, do you have a brother? Yes, perfect, good. Do you have a brother? Alaka akhun, good. So, what would be the answer? Now, I have a brother. Now, now, now, I'm not? No, so you just add, so remember we learned a pronoun for me. What was the pronoun for me? Like, how do you say my book? Yeah, yeah. So, just add that to the lamb. Just say it, just, no, because the Hamza
[SPEAKER_00] is for a question. Yeah, akhun, yeah, because akhi means my brother, right? So, you just say li akhun, I have a brother. Good, mashallah. Okay, brother, uncle. Alaka akhun, yeah. Do you have a sister? Mm-hmm. Naam, li akhun. Good, mashallah. Naam, li akhun. Yes, I have a sister. Good. What is gonna be akhun? Yeah, akhun, yeah. Why do you say akhun? I don't akhti. No, because normally, see, we hear these words like akhi, well, akhti, so that's why we might get confused. But we only hear it that often because akhi means my brother. So, usually when people are addressing others, they say akhi, akhi, like my brother, right? But the actual word is akhun, right? If you don't add a pronoun to it, it's akhun. When you say akhi, you add the ya to it. Right, like this. Helix?
[SPEAKER_00] What was that all about? Oh, okay. I was like, what is a helix? Okay. So, what was I gonna write? Oh, yeah. So, that's what you're saying. That means my sister. So, if you just want to say sister, you just say akhtun. Like that. Get it? Same thing with akhi, right? If it was akhi, then it would be like this. Akhi. But if you're just saying akhun, then it would just be akha. I wouldn't have that ya at the end. Like akhun. Okay? Got it? Alright. You can say akhi. Akhi is brother or my brother. That's what I'm saying. It's my brother. Okay. Akhun is just brother. Okay. Yeah. Okay. Brother Salim? Uh. Sayyara? Sayyaratun? I have a sayyaratun now. I have a sayyaratun. Good. Okay. Car and yes, I have a car. Good. I
[SPEAKER_00] do have a car. Now, again, for objects, you would use anda, right? So, you wouldn't say li sayyara. You would normally, you would say andi sayyaratun, right? But you wouldn't say andi akhun, right? Or andi umun or andi abun or whatever. You would say li, right? For if you're talking about you having a... A relative, for example. Wait, does it mean... The sign of that can mean do you have or does it belong to? It means do you have. Yeah. So, if you wanted to ask, is this your car? Does this car belong to you? Then you would say, ahadi sayyaratun laka. Got it? So, if I wrote down li sayyaratun, that's wrong? That's not necessarily wrong. Because li is used for both car, like, sorry, objects. And also, it's used for human beings as well. So, that wouldn't necessarily be wrong. But the other way around would be wrong. Like, if we were to use anda
[SPEAKER_00] for a human being, like andi akhun, that would be wrong. But li sayyaratun is not wrong, necessarily. But normally, you use andi in that context, though. For objects. Yeah. Okay. Next. Next. Brother Hamad. You're Hafiz? Or no? Okay, good. Mashallah. Hafiz. We'll call you Hafiz. Okay. Li or... You try to use the same word that's used in the question in the answer. Good. Very good. Mashallah. Do you have a... What is a darraja? Bicycle. Bicycle, good. Yes, I have a bicycle. Good. Hafiz Ishan. I have a pen. Yes, I have a pen. Translate it. Do you have a pen? Yes, I have a pen. Good.
[SPEAKER_00] Batawhid. I have a notebook. Yes, I have a notebook. Okay. Translate. I don't have a notebook. I just say something. Oh. Who can tell, brother, what is daftar? Office. Not office. Yeah, notebook. Yeah. Office in Urdu. Yeah. But daftarun means notebook. Yes. Okay. Sorry? Abu katajirun. Abu katajirun. Mm-hmm. So if you want to say my father, how would you say it? Abuqa means... No, no, you don't... You say abi. Yeah. The kaf is only if you're asking about you, if you're saying the word you. Ka, it refers
[SPEAKER_00] to you. If you want to say my, you say abi, right? Yeah. So you don't have to say ana. Ana is out of the picture. Because once you say abi, you're already saying my. So ana is redundant at that point. So you just say abi tatajirun. Naam. Abi tatajirun. Naam. Abi tatajirun. Good. Mashallah. Okay. Let's start from the side. Brother Dawood. Sorry, what did you say? No, he's not a businessman. How do you say it? Yeah, that's going to come. You would use the word laysa, right? Abi laysa bitajirun. He is not... Or laysa tatajirun. He is not a businessman. So... But that didn't come up yet. That's going to come up. I'm not... I'm trying to remember. I think it comes in the second book. I don't think it comes here yet. Can you say ma huwa? You can say ma huwa too, yeah. Yeah, ma huwa bitajirun. Yeah, that's fine. There's the same meaning as laysa. So, I thought that was a question, right? So, I put la ismi abi ustadun.
[SPEAKER_00] Oh, you were saying la abi ustadun. Yeah, that works too, yeah. That works too, actually, yeah. You can just say la abi ustadun. You wouldn't say abu, but abi. No, I said it here. No, but I put la ismi abi ustadun. You don't have to put ism. Because ism means name, right? Oh. You just say... Abi ustadun. Abi ustadun. Perfect, yeah. Good. Yeah, exactly. You don't have to use laysa, actually. No, that didn't come to my mind, yeah. Okay. Yeah, hello. Min ayna Muhammadun? Min ayna Muhammadun. Muhammadun. Muhammad min al-Yemeni. Good. Muhammadun min al-Yemeni. All right, good. Ma lugatuhu. Okay. Lugati arabiyat. No, lugatuhu. Oh, his language. Lugatuhu arabiyat. Al-arabiyat, yeah. Yeah. Lugatuhu al-arabiyat. Right. His language is Arabic. All right, good. Do you have to answer the question here?
[SPEAKER_00] Or can you say his language is easy or difficult? At the max? No, because that would be if you're asking about the quality of his language. Like if you're asking about the easiness of his language, right? That's not what you're asking. You're asking what. Ma means what. So you're asking what it is. Do you get it? You're not asking about its easiness or its hardness. Do you get it? Yeah. Yeah. If you were to say, For example, how is his language? Then you could answer like, For example. Okay. Okay, good. Good. Inshallah. Where is his father? His father is in the house. All right. Inshallah. Mm-hmm. Mm-hmm. Mm-hmm.
[SPEAKER_00] The one that the pronoun is being attached to, right? For example, yes, Umm itself is female. The mother is female. But we're saying his mother. Do you get it? Oh, wait. Yeah, yeah, yeah. So you're not going to make the person whose mother is female just because it's... Right, okay. Yeah. I got it. Okay. And you're not Hamza too? Hamza too. Yeah, because it's one of those male names that since it has a ta, it's similar to a female name. So therefore, it will follow the rule of female name, which is that it doesn't have tanween. Hamza too, Talha too, Usama too. Those are... We did in this lesson that those are a few names
[SPEAKER_00] that because it has a ta marbuta at the end, they will not have tanween. So it would just be Usama too, Hamza too, Talha too, like that. Hamza, where are you from? No, Min ayna Hamza too. Min ayna Hamza too. Where is Hamza? Yeah, good. Where is Hamza from? Oh, where is Hamza from? Yeah. Amin, yeah. Good. Very good. He is also from Hamza. Very good. Mashallah. I mean, sorry, from India. Good. Mashallah. Brother Jibreel. What's the next one? Yeah. Yeah. Ma lugatuhu. Okay, good. Ma lugatuhu al-Arabiya. Good. He's from India, but he knows Arabic. So, good. Mashallah. All right. Brother, are you ready to
[SPEAKER_00] do the next one? Yeah. Okay. Ayna abuhu. Okay. I guess the father would like to stay in the car. Okay. All right. Brother Mukhtar. Ayna zayn abu. Ayna zayn abu. Mm-hmm. Mm-hmm. Mm-hmm. Mm-hmm. Mm-hmm. Mm-hmm. Okay, good. I thought you were going to say fil matbaqi. Okay, that's good, too. Yeah. Good. Zayn abu fil madrasati. Okay, good. Brother Jibreel. We can say hiya. Yeah, you can say hiya, too. You can say Zayn abu, or you can just say hiya, the pronoun referring to Zayn abu. That's fine, too. Ayna zawjuhah. Ayna zawjuhah. Is that a name? Zawj? Yeah, no. Zawj. Zawj. Who can remind the brother what zawj is? Wife. Wife. Wife. Wife. Wife. Wife. Wife. Spouse. Yeah, so it could be used for the male, the husband or the wife. So, zawj. Over here means husband.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah. Good. Fil bayti. Zawjuhah fil bayti. Good. Her husband is in the house. Okay. All right. Next brother, Haq. Haq. Haq. Haq. Zawjuhah mudarrisun. Mudarrisun. Mudarrisun. Good. Mashallah. Very good. Okay. Next. Now we're starting number two. Let's get down with it quick, inshallah. Da'afil faraghi fi ma yali al-dameer hu amha. So, place. Place in the blank either the pronoun that indicates towards male or female. He or she. Right? So, it's pretty simple. Not too difficult. Okay. So, let's see
[SPEAKER_00] number one. Hadi. Okay. Brother Shiraz, you can. Go ahead. Go ahead. Sorry? Sorry? What? How much would be one word that is equal to one word? Yedza. Oh. Okay. What is that? Ok. Can he even fall? I was scared. Can she sing? She can't play. Right. Right. Uh huh, right. Well, yesterday she sang that quote and she was feeling exhausted so, make her into as well. okay. and feeling short. Yeah, that's not right. No, no, no. Ismuhu is
[SPEAKER_00] for male. Ismuhah is for female. Yeah. Remember we talked about there's so many ayat in the Quran which Allah says that when we're referring to Allah for Him belongs the heavens and the earth. To Him belongs the heavens and the earth. Yeah, exactly. Very good. Yeah, good example. And you know, when we learn the dua of the salatul janazah, right? You say, اللهم اغفر له وارحمه وعافيه وعفو عنه But that's if it's a male. If it's a female, all you have to do is you change the pronoun to ها Right? So you say, اللهم اغفر له وارحمه وعافيه وعفو عنه وَأَكْرِمْ نُزُلَهَا وَوَسِّعْ مُدْخَلَهَا وَاغْسِلْهَا بِالْمَاءِ وَالثَلْجِ وَالْبَرْضِ وَنَقِيهَا But if you were to say it to a male, you would say,
[SPEAKER_00] اللهم اغفر له وارحمه وعافيه وعفو عنه وَأَكْرِمْ نُزُلَهُ وَوَسِّعْ مُدْخَلَهُ Because they're all referring back to that male. Whereas for the female, it's a very good example, right? So that's a good way for us to remember as well. So, everybody got that? Okay. These pronouns will come everywhere, right? So just learning these, you should pick up a lot of things in the Qur'an now. Yeah, اسمه أحمد. Yeah, good in the Qur'an. In Surah As-Saff. No, it's not wrong because that would be the plural form. Yeah. Especially if you're in the haram in Mecca and Medina, normally after every salah, you'll have a janazah for multiple people at once. So then it's good to say, اللهم اغفر لهم وارحمهم because that's the plural form. So that would encompass everybody. It's not necessarily wrong because I mentioned last class that
[SPEAKER_00] sometimes you use the plural pronoun for one person out of respect. For example, sometimes you say, السلام عليكم even though you're only talking to one person. Even though the original is to say, السلام عليك. That's what we say in the تشهد to نبي صلى الله عليه وسلم السلام عليك أيها النبي Peace be upon you, O Prophet. Right? But we can also say, we also say, السلام عليكم just out of respect. If you want to say it to one person, you can say, السلام عليكم. That wouldn't necessarily be wrong. Okay. So would that be the same thing like when we ask for اللهم أجلنا من الله or we say, اللهم أجلنا من الله Yeah. Yeah, exactly. That's fine too. All right. But Zain, you want to go? You want to give it a try? Yeah, number two. Good. مهندسون Good. So we hear you use a male pronoun. وابنهو Because محمد
[SPEAKER_00] is a doctor, he's the male. And we're talking about his son. So we say, وابنهو Good. أشاء الله But Zain, you went already? No. Okay. Okay. Yeah, you want to ask him to? Okay. Okay. You want to go, right? No, no, no. حضر رجل حضر رجل قبيل اسمه عبد الله Good. Masha'Allah. So translate it. Okay. Okay. Okay. Okay. This man is a big merchant. Yeah. His name is Abdullah. Good. His name is Abdullah. Good. All right. Yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_00] Phil, sorry. أمنتوا في الغرفة في الغرفة What? في الغرفة. في الغرفة. Good. في الغرفة التي كذا في. So is it أمه because we're talking about أمها Good. Good. أمها في المطبخ Okay. Good. All right. Masha'Allah. حافظ مؤمن أمي أشاء الله طبيبكم وأختها أمي ممرضتن Good. Translate. مائشة is a doctor and her sister is a nurse. Nurse. Yeah. ممرضتن is a male nurse. ممرضتن is a female nurse.
[SPEAKER_00] Is it واختها or واختها? This is واختها because remember I mentioned that if the Hamza has the Hamza to Qatar on it, Okay. If it has that Hamza sign, there's a sign that's the Hamza to Qatar, not Hamza to Wasl, meaning you pronounce it no matter what, regardless of the situation. So أخت that the Hamza in there would be Hamza to Qatar, meaning you pronounce it every time. Same thing with أخ, right? That Hamza there is also pronounced every time. Okay. حافظ أركاشة End it off. محمدو Okay. Okay. زميله زميل No, so there's no reason to make it فتحة, you just keep it ضم زميله زميله محمد Good. Yeah. زميله Okay. Good. Translate. Left from the classroom and
[SPEAKER_00] and he left with forgot with زميل Anybody remind him? زميل زميل زميل زميل Classmate. Yeah. And he left with his classmate. So, so, to make it clear, the doer, the one who's doing the leaving is زميل, right? So you said he left with his classmate, but actually you would translate it as his classmate left with him. Because معه that ضميل, that pronoun is going back to محمد. You get it? So, and the doer, the one who's doing the, خرج is زميله. You get it? So you would translate it like and محمد left from the classroom and his classmate left with him. You get it? It's a slight difference, but I mean, in terms of the end result is the same. But to be precise
[SPEAKER_00] in terms of who's doing what, we have to translate it properly. But yeah, good, Mashallah, overall. But you got زميله That was the main point of the sentence. Which is that it's his classmate, right? Because we're talking about محمد. So use the male pronoun for that. Okay, good. Mashallah. مطبخ Anybody remind us what a مطبخ is? Yeah. Okay. بلثقيف You didn't get to go yet, right? Just give us two examples for number three. The question was هاتي خمسة أسئة وأجوبة كالمثال آتي Basically bring two questions and answers according to this basically this format. Sorry? I couldn't do this one. Okay, but you can do it on the spot, I'm sure. So you're basically أعندك قلم نعم عندي قلم So just replace the word قلم with
[SPEAKER_00] any other object. أعندك سيارة نعم عندي سيارة Perfect. Yeah. Do you have a translator? Do you have a card? Yes. Yeah. So again, just just remind yourself that this is how you say like, do you have this? Yes, I have this. Do you have this? So this is the format how you say just copy paste and just fill in the blank with whatever object and you have you already know how to say this. Right? Okay. So you can now talk to the immigration officials when you're going for أمر Right? So if it's قول قول قول قول Yeah, good. Yeah, you can even go to the restaurants. You can say أعندك blank whatever food you want. Right? You just learn the word in English I mean in Arabic and you can now order food in any restaurant in Saudi. Right? Mashallah. So the proper translation
[SPEAKER_00] will be I have قلم or I do have قلم or pen I do have a pen or I have a pen? I have a pen. Yeah. نعم عندي قلم Yes, I have a pen. Yeah, right? Sorry? Yeah. Okay. One more example. أعندك أعندك أعندك درس درس أعندك درس عندك You say عندك أعندك درس درس نعم عندي درس Okay, good. Do you have a class? Yes, I have a class. All right. Can somebody else give me one more example? أعندك مدسر That's wrong. You can't use عند. نعم أعندك بريان نعم عندي بريان Okay. All right. That works. All right.
[SPEAKER_00] أعندك سرير نعم جنس Good. Good. أعندك سرير نعم عندي سرير Okay. Now let's say if the جواز السفر means passport. So let's say if the immigration official asks you أعندك جواز السفر How would you respond? حافظي شان أعندك جواز السفر Good. أعندك جواز السفر Good. So تأشيرة means visa. So براتوحيد If the immigration official was to ask you أعندك تأشيرة تأشيرة تأشيرة Good. أعندك تأشيرة تأشيرة Good. أعندك تأشيرة تأشيرة Good. All right. So now you can literally hold conversations. Right? أعندك تأشيرة تأشيرة No, because عندي automatically gives you that or you could say معي too because عندي doesn't necessitate that it's with you at the moment necessarily but I
[SPEAKER_00] mean it's pretty obvious if you're saying عندي then they would just be they would know that it's with you. I was joking earlier but the right way would be معاك Like do you as مدثر with you? Yeah. If you want to say as مدثر with you you say معاك because عند again we mentioned you don't use it for human beings. Right? You only use ل or لام for the human beings. Okay. All right. Now it's already half an hour passing. Number four. Now we have to do the opposite. أعندك قلم لا ما عندي قلم Right? Okay. أحفظ أثمان Give me one example from this. Good. أعندك كتاب لا ما عندي كتاب Good. Okay. أحفظ أكاشر Give me another example. Good. Brother Ali.
[SPEAKER_00] Very good. You guys remember what تفاح means? Apple, right? Do you have an apple? No, I do not have an apple. Okay. Good. One more example. Anybody? أعندك حديد عندك عندك عندك حديد لا نعندك حديد عندي عندي حديد حديد mean like an iron? Yeah. Like metal. Yeah. Okay. Good. Do you have metal? No, I don't have metal. Are you saying money? Money? مال نقو You can say مال نقو Mal is wealth, or do you want to be more specific, nukud is like, yeah, nukud, no, and dee, yeah, ma and dee nukud, good. Are you taking our answer?
[SPEAKER_00] He said la, he said he didn't have. Yeah, okay, all right. What if a person comes by and they go like this and they beg him, and you just say la, ma, dee, skip that part and go take the next part, like la, ma, dee, nukud? I mean, yeah, it makes sense, yeah. That's good. All right. Now, we already did. We did next to me already in class, right? Yeah. Okay. All the rest we did already? We didn't do that, right? Okay, so let's read that right now. Okay, can you read? Okay, good. Good.
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah. Again, ma means what? With, with, and remember, we have to focus on the fact that it will make the word after it kasra, it will make the word after it kasra, not because it's a harful jarb, because it's a dharf, remember, like, for example, tahtal maktabi, right? So it will have a fatha, maa, with a fatha, and it will make the word after it kasra, right? Because it's a dharf. Dharf means something that indicates time or purpose. Place. So maa normally indicates place, right? Something is with you. Could you also say if harf is a hamidun, be khwaad is it? So be gives a slightly different meaning. It means, like, you're, you're, basically, he's, like, taking him with, with him, kind of like, it doesn't necessarily mean involuntarily, but it's like, you're taking, it's like you're taking him, you get
[SPEAKER_00] it? Whereas maa ha just means you're together. It doesn't necessarily. It doesn't necessarily mean that you're the one who's taking him. You get it? Because that's the difference. So it's similar meaning, but not exactly the same. Okay. All right. Next. Anybody else who wants to volunteer? Yeah. Yeah. Good. Good. Very good. The doctor went with the engineer. Dhahaba, again, we learned it. It's a verb that means to go, right? So, what does it mean? Dhahaba tabeebu? Or it would be dhahaba al-tabeebu? Yeah, you're right. Dhahaba tabeebu. Right? Because it's the hamad al-wasl. Good. All right. Next. Mujala sal mudirikum al-masheeri. Mudiri, yeah. What was the translation? The teacher is sitting with the teacher. Yeah. This is
[SPEAKER_00] a past tense verb, so you would say sat. Teacher sat with the... Principal, very good. Is this the same thing as like jalsa? Jalsa, jalsa? It's from the same root word, yeah. Jalsa, because, you know what? Jalsa is a position in salah in which you sit down, right? So, that's why it's from the same root word. Jalsa is the verb, and jalsa is what you call in English the gerund. Like, it's like the... The noun? Yeah, the noun. Yeah, verbal noun, I think you call it. Okay. Next. Number four. Good. Is it... Good. Because remember, we learned that ya, when you add ya to something, then it becomes dhamma, right? You would say, yeah. For example, yeah, yeah. So, sorry. So, you translated it good. Yeah. Who is with you? Man ma'ak. Who is with you?
[SPEAKER_00] Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. You can say... So, in Tajweed, if you're reciting Quran, you would say man ma'ak, right? But when you're speaking normal Arabic, the rules of Tajweed do not apply. So, you would just say man ma'ak. Yeah. The rule of Tajweed meaning... It doesn't mean that you just mispronounce all the letters, right? Of course, like the makharij of the huruf, like the way you pronounce the letters should be correct, right? Like... So, it's clearly different. It's clearly differentiated between daad and dhal and dha and za. They could all be mixed up if you don't pronounce it properly. But when I say the rule of Tajweed, they don't apply, meaning you don't have mud. You're not stretching, right? Like al-a, like you don't stretch it, right? And similarly, you don't have to do ikhfa, right? All right. Like you don't say min qabli when you're having a conversation, right? So, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] So, in the same way, you wouldn't say man ma'ak, right? Although you might hear Arabs saying it just to kind of like say it quicker. So, it's not necessarily wrong in that particular context. But again, you wouldn't do a proper ghunna, right? You wouldn't do it in man ma'ak, right? You're not going to say it like that, right? So, yeah. See, ma'i is the meaning. Ma'i is like, I am good. No. Just translate it like literally. Like it says, what does ma'ak mean? With you. So, ma'i means? Yeah. So, then. So, translate it accordingly. So, ma'i ma'ak ya'ad. Who is with you? Ma'i zameeli. Ma'i won't be just pointing to myself, right? Yeah. I am with my classmates. No, no. Again, just translate ma'i. What does ma'i mean?
[SPEAKER_00] Okay. Zameeli. Classmates. Classmates. Classmates. So, not just. That's what is in the middle. Oh, classmate is with me. Yeah. Good. All right. Last one. It sounds like classmate is with me. Or I am with my. Sorry. My classmate is with me. Yeah. Yeah. Why does zameeli come second? It means my classmate is with me. So, I think I mentioned this to you guys before. That the thing that's being asked about normally, it comes first. Right? So, over here, you're asking man ma'aka, right? So, because of that, you're going to make that come first. You get it? Yeah. Okay. Okay. Last one. Anybody? Anybody?
[SPEAKER_00] No. Ma'aha. What does ma'aha mean? Yeah. So, you would say amina with her is? No. So, you're not saying she is with her spouse. Because that would be aminatu ma'a zawjiha. Right? But this is slightly different. Saying ma'aha zawjuha. You get the difference? Wait. What did you say? Aminata. So, if we were to translate it as amina is with her spouse, then you would say aminatu ma'a zawjiha. Right? But that's not what it's saying here. It's saying aminatu ma'aha zawjuha. Slight difference, but it makes a difference in the translation. Spouse means ma'a. No. What's the English translation for aminatu ma'a? That's what I'm asking him. Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00] Anybody want to try it? So, she is, amina is with her husband somewhere? No. No. No. So, the little meaning is with amina is her husband. Right? So, her husband is with her. Amina is her spouse is with her? Yeah. Yeah, basically. Ma'aha with her is her spouse, basically. With her spouse. Yeah. That's how you would translate it like literally, literally. But yeah. Her spouse is with her. Her spouse is with her. Again. It comes to the same thing, but we want to learn how to translate accurately because then we'll understand it accurately. With amina is her husband. Exactly. So, the answer is amina's spouse is with her. Is that the answer? No, because then that would be aminatu ma'a zawjuha. So, then. So, yeah. You're right. Actually, you're right. That's how you translate it. Sorry. Yeah. Yeah, you're right. Yeah. Shouldn't it be zawjuha since ma'a comes before it? No, because the word. So, ma'a. So, ma'a is the
[SPEAKER_00] effect of ma'a is transferred to the ha, right? And since these are dhamirs, these are pronouns, they don't turn into kasra. So, then basically it's like you could say it kind of gets negated. The effect of ma'a gets negated. So, if you attach a pronoun to ma'a like ma'aka or ma'i, so then it doesn't make whatever comes after that kasra anymore. Get it? Okay. Sorry. There was one more actually. So, um would be mother, but am is different. Good. Yeah. My uncle. Specifically, which uncle? Because there's two types of uncles. Mother's side or father's side? Huh? Mother's side. No,
[SPEAKER_00] paternal. Yeah, from the father's side. Am means from the father's side. And what was the mother's side? Khal. Khal means the uncle from the mother's side. Okay. Good. Mashallah. All right. I'm sorry. Can you, so he left his uncle? That's the translation? Yeah. Khal is with him. Am is with him. No. No, my uncle left with him. Yeah. Okay. All right. This next one we don't need to go over. We already went over. Betun means a house. Or let's just have somebody quickly translate each line. Go ahead. Betun, a house, Betuta, your house, Betu, his house, Betula, her house, Beti, my house. Very good. Okay. Who wants to do the next line? Abun, a father, Abuka,
[SPEAKER_00] your father, Abubu, his father, Abula, her father, Abi, my father. Good. Mashallah. Akhun, yes. A sister. Sister? He told me sister, so somehow. Where is Akhubi? Brother, brother, brother. I mean, you raised your hand. I assume you would know. Your brother. It's brother, right? Yes, brother. You got to say it, man. He's telling me it's his sister. But you got to say it in Arabic. Oh, okay. A brother, your brother. Wait, say it in Arabic. Akhuka, she's like, say it. Oh, oh. Akhu, a brother. Akhun. Oh, sorry. Akhun, a brother. Akhuka, your brother. Akhubu, his brother. Akhuha, her brother. And Afi, your brother. Very good. Mashallah. Good.
[SPEAKER_00] Okay, we're recording in three minutes. We have two, three minutes. Okay. Let's just... I was hoping to finish the next lesson, but we didn't even get started in the next lesson. Let's just finish these last few things and Abiyu wa ummi filbayt. Somebody just read and translate then. I think it's good to just... Abiyu wa ummi filbayt. Abiyu wa ummi filbayt. Filbayt. Tu or ta or ti? Filbayti. Good, yeah. My father and my mother is in the house. Are in the house, yes. Are in the house. Aina abuka... We'll just do one by one. Anybody else? Aina abuka ya hamidu. Good. Dahaba ila al-supi. Good. Where is your father, O Hamid? He went towards
[SPEAKER_00] the market. Very good. Masha'Allah. Good. Akuka tabibun. Is your brother a doctor? No, he is an engineer. Not engineer. Teacher, yes. Good. Zaynabu fil riyaadhi. Akhuha fil taayti. Babuha fil madinatil munawwalat. Very good. Translate. Zaynabu is in Riyadh. Her brother is in Bayan. And her father is in Madinatul Munawwalat. Good. Very good. Masha'Allah. Next. Next. Khazat talibu abuhu waziru wa akuhu taajirun tabiri. He is a student. Mm-hmm.
[SPEAKER_00] Let the brother say it, because we want him to figure it out himself. He can do it. He can do it. This student's father is a minister. And his brother is a big minister. Good. Very good. Masha'Allah. This student, his father, his father is a minister, and his brother is a big merchant. Very good. No, it would be wazirun. Because it's the khabar, right? The predicate. So it would be wazirun. Wazirun wouldn't be advisor? You wouldn't say advisor? Advisor. It could be. Like, it just means somebody who's not the main leader, but he's like the, somebody who's a co, like a... The governor. A governor. It could be a governor. It could be. It depends on, like, the... But yeah, minister is a better translation, though. Deputy minister, what day? Yeah. Okay. Next,
[SPEAKER_00] number six. Quick, quick, quick. Let's get done. Okay, good. My brother went to the school, and he went. My brother went. My brother? And my father went to... Okay, must be a young father. Or he's just trying to study even when he gets older. Translate? Oh, you're sorry, you re-translated. Okay. Next. Okay, this next few, all they're doing is explaining to you the thing that I mentioned before, that generally for male names, you'll put a tanween. Muhammadun, Khalidun, Hamidun, Abbasun, Mahmoodun. However, if it has a tamarbuta, remember tamarbuta, tamarbuta is this type of taa.
[SPEAKER_00] So it's either like this, or it's like this, right? Tamarbuta, right? So normally that's an indication that something is female, right? Faltimatu, right? Or mumaridlatun, right? Tabibatun. So that's normally an indication of something female. So remember we mentioned the general for female names is what? That they don't get tanween, right? Right. So the same thing, there's some male names that have feminine qualities, meaning it has a tamarbuta, right? So for these names, they follow the same pattern as female names. So therefore, they will not get tanween. For example, Hamzatun, Talhatun, Usamatun, Muawiatun, Ikrimatun. And part of this would also be Rukashatun, right? Rukashatun, your name would also be part of this. So it's a family. Mashallah. Trying to think of anybody else here.
[SPEAKER_00] Uthman. No, not Uthman, Uthman. No. Hamzayat. Yeah, Hamzayat. Yeah. So anyways, we just need to remember this. Now, you read the following names. Somebody just read this quickly. Malidun, Hamzatun, Amarun. Anasun, Muawiatun, Hamidun. Usamatun, Ikrimatun. Ikrimatun, yeah. Abbasun, Muhammadun, Talhatun. Good. Okay, we get in class here, inshallah. We will start from lesson number 11 on Monday, inshallah ta'ala. I can't let you guys go without homework because you have all the way to... Today's Monday? Oh, I'm bugging you. Sorry. My bad. Sorry about that. Okay. Okay. So, okay, no homework then. If you want to do homework, what you're going to do is bring five examples or as many examples as you want. of each pronoun from the Qur'an. Ka and Hu and Ha and
[SPEAKER_00] Ya. Bring a few examples, whatever, however many you want, of each Nughar. That's optional homework if you want to do it and benefit more, inshallah. And it's fine. Allah is the Greatest. It's fine. Allah is the Greatest. And there is no God but Allah. And there is no God but Allah.